Register of the Nikolai Nikolaevich Lebedev Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Nikolai Nikolaevich Lebedev papers,
1920-1980
2001C53
Lebedev, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1905-1980
8 microfilm reels (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Financial records, minutes, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to charitable activities on behalf of Russian immigrants in the United States. Includes records of the Russian Benevolent Trust Fund in Memory of V. P. and M. P. Anitchkoff.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biographical Note
1905 April 5 (N.S.) Born, Chita, Russia
1944 Naturalized as an American citizen
1947-1979 Treasurer, Russian Benevolent Trust Fund in Memory of V. P. and M. P. Anitchkoff
1980 January 26 Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
N. N. Lebedev was active in several Russian organizations in San Francisco from the 1940s to the 1970s, particularly in the Russian Benevolent Trust Fund in Memory of V. P. and M. P. Anitchkoff, of which he was treasurer during the entire period of its existence (1947-1979). This organization aided recent Russian immigrants, especially those arriving from China following the Second World War, and Lebedev's papers reflect its activities in this respect. The SUBJECT FILE also contains a small amount of material relating to N. N. and A. I. Lebedev's participation in social and cultural organizations such as the Russian Women's Home of Mercy (1940s) and Den' russkogo rebenka celebrations in San Francisco in the 1970s.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russians--United States.; Charities--United States.; Russia.; United States.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Russian Benevolent Trust Fund in Memory of V. P. and M. P. Anitchkoff.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1929-1980. (Box 1)
  Awards, clippings, employment records, family file, identity papers, income tax returns, and marriage certificates, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Russian Benevolent Trust Fund in Memory of V.P. and M.P. Anitchkoff, 1947-1974. (Box 1-8)
  Correspondence, financial records and minutes of meetings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Subject File, 1920-1976. (Box 8)
  Albums, clippings, correspondence, and programs, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, undated. (Box 9)
  Numerous prints depicting N. N. and A. I. Lebedev, together and separately and in groups, as well as Den' russkogo rebenka celebrations and meetings of the Harbin Polytechnic Alumni Association. Not filmed
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1929-1980 (Box 1)
  - Awards (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings about N. N. Lebedev (Folder 1: 2)
  - Employment records (Folder 1: 3)
  - Family file - Lebedev (Kvitko), Anna Ivanovna
    - Death certificate. (Folder 1: 4)
      Includes memorial resolution of the Laundry, Dry Cleaning and Dye House Workers International Union, Local 26
    - Employment records (Folder 1: 5)
    - Identity papers. (Folder 1: 6)
      Includes copy and English translation of birth certificate, and certificate of naturalization
  - Identity papers. (Folder 1: 7)
    Includes English translation of birth certificate, certificate of naturalization, driver's license and various other identification and insurance cards
  - Income tax returns (Folder 1: 8)
  - Marriage certificates (Folder 1: 9)
- RUSSIAN BENEVOLENT TRUST FUND IN MEMORY OF V. P. AND M. P. ANITCHKOFF, 1947-1974
  - Correspondence (Folder 1: 10)
  - Financial records
    - General (Folder 1: 11)
    - Bank books (Folder 1: 12)
    - Bank statements
      - 1947-1950 (Folder 1: 13)
      - 1951-1952 (Folder 1: 14)
      - 1953-1957 (Folder 1: 15)
      - 1958-1963 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Checkbooks
      - 1947-1952 (Folder 2: 2)
      - 1952-1955 (Folder 2: 3)
      - 1955-1963 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Ledgers
      - 1947-1952 (Folder 2: 5)
      - 1952-1960 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Loan control records
      - Cardex (Folder 3: 2)
      - Lists (Folder 3: 3-4)
    - Receipt books
      - 1947-1952 (Folder 3: 5)
      - 1952-1954 (Box-folder 4: 1)
      - 1954-1957 (Folder 4: 2)
      - 1957-1962 (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1962-1970 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Minutes of meetings (with attachments)
    - General. Notes, 1965-1974 (Folder 5: 2)
    - 1947 (Folder 5: 3)
    - 1948 (Folder 5: 4)
    - 1949
      - January-August (Folder 5: 5)
      - September-December (Folder 6: 1)
    - 1950
      - January-March (Folder 6: 2)
      - April-December (Folder 6: 3)
    - 1951
      - January-May (Folder 6: 4)
      - June-December (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - 1952 (Folder 7: 2)
    - 1953 (Folder 7: 3)
    - 1954 (Folder 7: 4)
    - 1955 (Folder 7: 5)
    - 1956-1958 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - 1959 and 1961 (Folder 8: 2)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1920-1976
  - Den' russkogo rebenka. (Folder 8: 3)
    Clippings and programs
  - Klodnitskaia, Galina. (Folder 8: 4)
    Two albums of poems and autographs
  - Russian Women's Home of Mercy (Zhenskii dom miloserdiia), San Francisco, California. (Folder 8: 5)
    Clippings and correspondence relating to the running of the home and fundraising activities
  - Miscellany. (Folder 8: 6)
    Clippings on the death of N. V. Borzov and A. N. Vagin and two rare Russian brochures, issued in China on Russian language and word games
- PHOTOGRAPHS, undated., Not filmed. (Box 9)
  Numerous prints depicting N. N. and A. I. Lebedev, together and separately and in groups, as well as Den' russkogo rebenka celebrations and meetings of the Harbin Polytechnic Alumni Association